<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honesty is the best policy</title>
            <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L739A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43362</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27296932</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27296932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1724:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honesty is the best policy</title>
                  <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Lawton by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1660-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110066:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>HONESTY IS THE BEST POLICY.</head>
            <byline>by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Laughton of the Temple.</byline>
            <p>THO Men are ſo tranſported, yet nevertheleſs I will at this Juncture endeavour to ſhew every Party what infinite <hi>Hazards</hi> they have run, what great <hi>Loſſes</hi> they have ſuſtained, by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Notions, unreaſonable Averſions and Bigottries; and becauſe I would yet heal and compoſe all our <hi>Differences,</hi> I ſhall avoid all Sarcaſm, and Levity of Expreſſion, and likewiſe becauſe I rather conſider the Diſpute between the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> than between <hi>Him</hi> and the P. of <hi>Orange:</hi> For I believe no unbyaſſed wiſe Man can, even now in his Conſcience, think the Prince has dealt Honourably or Religiouſly by his Wives Father, and his own Uncle, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>Cameronian</hi> Reflector, where he talks of the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt Kingdoms and Families, had proved it more lawful to ſteal Crowns than Trifles, or rob ſo near Relations than other Men The <hi>King</hi> and Mankind muſt forgive me if Juſtice command <hi>infandum renovare dolorem,</hi> to look a little into the Cauſes of the late <hi>Civil Wars.</hi> I am the fartheſt Man alive from juſtifying the execrable Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, but on the other hand I cannot ſay the People began that War without great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations from the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of thoſe days. I believe the Laws of <hi>England</hi> make the Kings of it unaccountable in their own Perſons: But the <hi>Monopolies,</hi> the <hi>Loans,</hi> the <hi>Ship-money,</hi> and <hi>illegal Impriſonments, &amp;e.</hi> were real Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances: How fatal that War was, both to the <hi>King</hi>'s and <hi>Parliament</hi> Party; how horrid in the Iſſue of it, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Royal Blood,</hi> may be read in our <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> and is felt in our <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> But whence originally came all thoſe Misfortunes? If any Man tells me long Stories of the <hi>Religious Contentions,</hi> I muſt confeſs I blame them, and I allow they had their weight; but I take the Root of thoſe great Evils to proceed from Defects in our <hi>Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution:</hi> I will point out the <hi>Defects;</hi> but I neither have Authority, nor Genius, to propoſe the <hi>Remedies.</hi> Ever ſince King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's time, the Nature and Element of the Engliſh Government have been altered, All Regular Governments (call them, and let the Titles of their Magiſtracy be what you pleaſe) partake of all the three ſeveral Sorts, but there are in all Climates eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings and flowings of the <hi>Monarchical, Ariſtocratical,</hi> and <hi>Democratical</hi> Particles of the Compoſure, and all the Counſels of State muſt be proportioned to thoſe Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Take a view of our Government before <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's time, and you find a <hi>Monarch</hi> whoſe Baſis is <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> but if you will reflect ſolidly how he has ſtood ſince, it is upon the Foot of the People: Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> underſtood this, and govern'd happily, and her Miniſters <hi>Cecil, Eſſex, Rawleigh, Walſingham, &amp;c.</hi> were leſs her <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> than they were the <hi>Favourites</hi> of the People. Tho her Title was diſputable, <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> but new, <hi>Spain</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful and ambitious; by perſuing large Meaſures, and taking beloved Men into her Counſels, and by ſuffering them to Adviſe honeſtly, ſhe was too hard for all the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties ſhe met with, and, after a long Reign, lay'd down her Head in <hi>Peace;</hi> I think <hi>Princes</hi> may learn Leſſons out of her Life, Yet I will not be her <hi>Panygeriſt,</hi> for I think ſhe was ſometimes <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> but herein I think ſhe Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to wit, That when any thing began to be generally misliked, ſhe ſoon heard the Voice of the <hi>People,</hi> and gave way to the impetuoſity of National Diſcontents, and ſo was a greater Miſtreſs of <hi>Crown-craft</hi> than moſt of her Predeceſſors, or thoſe that ſucceeded her. K. <hi>Charles</hi> the I. tho a Prince of many Royal Virtues, was a little too tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of his Purpoſes, and thought himſelf a greater Judg of National Exigencies than a Houſe of Commons think any King ought to be; and after all the Schemes of the Schools, and the Advices of Flatterers, no King of theſe Kingdoms can ſit ſure, that is not well with <hi>Parliaments.</hi> There are Propenſities to which all Conſtitutions of State muſt be adjuſted, and the <hi>Bodies of Men</hi> will every where be too hard for all Speculations. A thirſt after <hi>Liberty</hi> expell'd the Kings of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there were Indications of almoſt abſolute <hi>Monarchical</hi> Diſpoſitions in the Factions of <hi>Marius, Scylla,</hi> and <hi>Catiline,</hi> before <hi>Ceſar</hi>'s perpetual Dictatorſhip; The Revolt of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> from the <hi>Spaniſh Government,</hi> when in all its height and ſtrength, ſhews no Armies can be too hard for Univerſal Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and is a <hi>Memento</hi> to all Crowned Heads, That where a Monarch will ſtrain the bonds of Government in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of the People, they will break them. When the Barons were able to make War upon ſlight Pretences, if the Kings kept fair with the Barons they were ſafe, but the Crown, the Barons, and the greater Gentry ſince the Barons, could ſell their Lands, and the Court of Wards has been taken away, and the Crown has diſpoſed of its Lands; can govern no longer Securely than they have Reputation with the People. Government muſt follow in a great meaſure the Nature of the Tenures, and there muſt be an <hi>Agrarian</hi> Law for Power where the Lands are ſo diſtributed: You ſee I have ſtarted many bold Hints, but I am not willing to draw them out at length, nor to write over cloſely where I may endanger the good Opinion of all Sides: But I will conclude upon this point, That ſince the Princes have had an Inclination to greater Power than the People will comply with; and the People a ſtronger <hi>Luſt</hi> after <hi>Liberty</hi> than our Kings were willing to ſatisfie; That the one has miſtaken Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and the other as much their Privileges, it would be well if a New <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was made to explain, and aſſert each; This would be a happy Concluſion of our Troubles; This would turn our Swords into Plow ſhares, and has been heretofore the more warrantable product of thoſe Stirs that Male-adminiſtrations occaſioned. Thus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110066:2"/>our Parliaments could not be corrupted, nor our judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Proceedings precarious; Engliſhmen have now an Opportunity to ſecure theſe good Things, For ſince Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has it ſelf been pleaſed ſo to order it, that the <hi>King</hi> has been defeated in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> have received ſo great a Loſs at Sea, we have no longer reaſon to dread a <hi>French</hi> or an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Conqueſt; and the <hi>King</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but now know, That he can never come to wear the Crowns of theſe Nations, unleſs he will make ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſentions as are proper for our Circumſtances, as are neceſſary to ſecure both our <hi>Religion,</hi> and our <hi>Property.</hi> I have been with him ſince his <hi>Exile,</hi> and the laſt Words he ſaid to me were, That he ſent me home to make a <hi>BAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAIN</hi> with his People; But I did not meet with People whoſe Minds were prepared to propoſe juſt and equitable Expedients. He knows I would not make ill Conditions for my Country; I have been ſuſpected of being over nice and zealous for it, I confeſs I am more concerned for its Welfare than for all my own neareſt and deareſt Intereſts; yet I can very well comply with the Equal and Hereditary Monarchy of <hi>England.</hi> I never was an Enemy to the word Monarchy, nor deſign'd to interrupt the Succeſſion of the Crown; nor do I think it the Intereſt of any Man that loves Peace, and theſe Nations, to do it: On the contrary, I at this day affirm, tho we ought always to have expected Terms from King <hi>James,</hi> or have ſent them to him, We ought not (tho I would have good Ones) even now to make ſuch as would make him juſtly Uneaſy; ſo unreaſonable Ones, as would be unfit for him to grant, We muſt deal impartially, if we would ever compoſe Things; We ought to ſhew our Claim, or at leaſt our Neceſſity, and we ought to couch Things in ſuch Words, as tho they ſpeak plainly our Senſe, may have a due Regard to his Dignity. <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> have been preached to him, as the certain Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of his Throne: He has been humbled by Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions: He has heard of his Miſtakes, and has hearkned to free Advice: He has Reaſon to have it, and he has Temper, and perhaps both he and we may be the better for our Tribulations, if we once accommodate our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes. I never flattered the <hi>King;</hi> I have ſpoken plainer to him than I write now, and I believe I am not the leſs acceptable to him for my Plainneſs: And as to any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection and Scruple that may be raiſed by a Declaration that is Publiſhed in his Name, I muſt ſay, I know no more than he that Reflects upon it, whether it be King <hi>Jame</hi>'s Declaration or no: For about three Years ſince, there was a Declaration Publiſhed in his Name, and for the Spreading of which ſeveral People were Impriſoned, That I was afterwards told by the Author King <hi>James</hi> knew nothing of. And I muſt ſay further, That that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that has been lately Publiſhed does not anſwer to the Spirit I left him in many Months ago; for, as I ſaid, he told me he ſent me to make a<note n="*">The Word BARGAIN is a term of condiſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.</note> 
               <hi>BARGAIN,</hi> to know what it was his People would have. I can't anſwer for what Accounts other People ſent him; but I am ſure he will ſo far juſtify me, as to ſay I have been ever againſt excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Mens <hi>Lives</hi> or <hi>Fortunes.</hi> I have been ever for being very Explanative about the Liberties of my Country, and if any body with him, or any here, have led him into Meaſures that are diſguſtful to the People, I think I may boldly aver, It is Miſinformation, and not Malice, that makes him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vable to Miſconſtruction. Thoſe that wiſh for the beſt Things are the ſhyeſt, have ever been too ſhy towards him; and it is not impoſſible that this Government may bribe Some body to give too plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Names and Reaſons for thoſe Things that may turn to the <hi>King</hi>'s Prejudice, as ſome did here before the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came: But the day that he really refuſes from any ſort of Men, that can ſhew a probability of bringing him home, any Propoſals that have tendency to Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Good, he gives leave to his Subjects to have recourſe to the Laws of Self-preſervation; Then, and not till then, he <hi>Abdicates</hi> his Crown. This is ſpeaking plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> you ſee I ſpeak plainly concerning what the <hi>King</hi> muſt do; Therefore let me alſo ſpeak ſome plain Truths, and rehearſe ſome Matters of Fact, to my Countrymen. And here I will begin with aſſerting, That if the People would be true to themſelves at the Reſtauration, and careful i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Elections of Members to Parliament, we need no other Treaty, but what the <hi>King</hi> will be forc'd to make good in the firſt <hi>Seſſions.</hi> We need not fear <hi>French,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Papiſts;</hi> We are too large and too brave a Country t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be a Plantation; <hi>France</hi> cannot ſpare from off the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Men enough to govern us contrary to our Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And tho our Hiſtories talk of our being Conquered any Man of Senſe ſees it was by Compoſition; It was from Parties within, and not from Force without us. As for the Roman Catholicks their Numbers are inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and tho they have good Eſtates, and ſome Men of great Natural Sagacity amongſt them; yet their having been out of Buſineſs keeps them from underſtanding the Knack and Turns of it: And, whatever weak People think a King of that Perſwaſion in a Proteſtant Country is more properly than any other Laws can make him a <hi>de bene pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cito</hi> King. Sir <hi>Will. Temple</hi>'s Obſervations upon the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and his Eſſay upon Governments, can never be too often read by Prince, or People: The one may be taught by it how to Govern, and the other cured of unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fears. Standing Armies are the juſteſt dread to Civil Liberties, but they are many ways as dangerous to Kings as they can be to their People. A beloved General may turn their Competitor, and every Mutiny ſhakes their Thrones: And the King that will make his Subjects Slaves by their hands, muſt be as much and more a Slave to them. If the Troops are Foreign he muſt be the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary and Vaſſal of that Prince who lends them; and if they are home-bred Forces, the Diſpoſitions of the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace will infect the Army: But beſides all this, no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, tho they may maintain Forces enough to ſuppreſs a ſudden Inſurrection, can poſſibly maintain enough to govern contrary to the general Genius of the Nation. The People of <hi>Turky</hi> hold all their Lands of the Crown, and like their Government; and as for the Peaſante of <hi>France,</hi> they talk daily of their grand Monarch. An ill concerted Conſpiracy may miſcarry. Hot-headed Men may expect too ſoon to fire their Country-men, but ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Diſſatisfactions are no more to be withſtood than general Conflagrations: When Neceſſity and Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation arm Men, let their Weapons be what they will, they will cur their way through all Oppoſition. Indeed if a People are divided, as we are, the Danger muſt be common, or very notorious, before they make uſe of their <hi>Intrinſick Power.</hi> But if ſome Laws were enacted to keep Eccleſiaſtick Controverſies out of the Pulpit, and the People were not taught to believe what in caſes of Extremity humane Nature will never practiſe. If Divines are not ſuffered to diſpoſe of the Kingdoms of this World, Civil Crimes and Rights will be ſoon called by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Names, and we ſhall recover our Liberties in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary way before Things grow deſperate: It is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, and ought to be criminal, for them to pretend to ſet out the Boundaries of Government: They may preach in general ſubmiſſion to Authority, but they are not to bring Texts of Scripture, and much leſs <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <hi>Ideas,</hi> or <hi>Zenophon</hi>'s <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to overthrow our <hi>Statute-books,</hi> and depretiate the Laws of <hi>England.</hi> By an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the time of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, no Man that was not Batchellor in Divinity was to preach about Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, or Free-will, becauſe that Controverſy then troubled the Church; and ſure I am, That the Clergy of no Degree ought to preach about the Prerogative, and our Privileges. Their Stake is not generally great enough to keep them from Flattery and ſiniſter Interpretations, by which too many of their Predeceſſors have been raiſed to Church-Dignities. They underſtand not our Laws, nor have they much credit for theſe Reaſons with the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110066:2"/>People; and they ought now to have leſs, ſince ſo many of their Coat have <hi>prevaricated.</hi> In a word, They ought by their Function to underſtand the Myſteries of Religion, and leave the <hi>Arcana Imperii</hi> to the Lay-men. They ought to be puniſhed if they call Men Idolaters, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Fanaticks, Rebels, Traytors, Seditious Perſons, with the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of their <hi>Billingsgate</hi> Rhetorick. Liberty of of Conſcience will make one part ill Manners, and Crimes againſt the State are proper for the Cognizance of the Civil Power; nor do I believe it was ever better'd by the Interpoſition of any Sort of Prieſts: Nor indeed is Religion it ſelf the better for the Affectation of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of that Robe to intermeddle with Matters meerly Temporal. But God knows they are too often buzzing, that this and that Thing is Republican; and they have needleſs Apprehenſions for their Church. As for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth Principles, ſcarce any body carrys them ſo far as to be againſt having a Single Perſon at the Head of our Affairs; and as for chopping and changing Kings, or rebelling when their is Occaſion, I do not find the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſo much behind hand with any other Sect: She can lead the Dance, and tho ſhe may pretend Wearineſs before it is at an end, yet ſhe can comply for Company. But after all this is ſaid, I think her of all the ſeveral Churches the beſt for this Nation, and ſo do almoſt all Engliſh-men; which leads me, as the Parſons Phraſe it, to ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of her Fears. As much as the Church of <hi>England</hi> Men have carreſſed and writ for an Arbitrary Power, <hi>NOTHING ELSE CAN PULL DOWN THEIR CHURCH;</hi> and ſhe might ſee by what followed the two Tolerations ſince the <hi>Royal Blood</hi> was Reſtored, That however ſhe has treated the Diſſenters, they will never joyn to pull down the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and let in <hi>Popery:</hi> Nor will ſhe ever again be worm'd out of her Diſcipline, if ſhe never yields to Comprehenſion, <hi>OR IS NOT TOO PLAINLY AN ENEMY TO CIVIL SECURITIES.</hi> But I have made too long a Digreſſion; and perhaps ſome may uncharitably think I like too much the ſubject Matter of it, but I only deſign the good of the Clergy, and the general Peace of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> No Man can have a greater value than my ſelf for all thoſe of that Order that are ſerious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and Sufferers for their Principles; but if they will conſider how many of thoſe that were in the late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> and in this <hi>Revolution,</hi> went conſtantly to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they will not think it very Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable for <hi>Princes</hi> to govern themſelves by ſuppoſing that that Men will live up to Doctrines that (I ſhall not ſay) are miſtaken in Idea; but only aſſert that they are too Self-denying to be expected in practice from our profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Age. I make profeſſion of great Plainneſs, but I beg a candid interpretation from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for what I have ſaid; And from the <hi>Whigs</hi> of all Sorts for what I am about to ſay to them. I think they have not made the wiſeſt Uſe of the Kings they have quarrelled with, and that they are too frantickly Apprehenſive of Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. There are great Lengths that all Mankind will go with them. Many of the Church of <hi>England</hi> joyn'd with their Principles at the beginning of the late <hi>Civil Wars;</hi> and their Conſciences did not miſgive them, till they had humbled that <hi>unfortunate Prince</hi> into ſuch <hi>Conceſſions</hi> as would have effectually ſecured the <hi>Rights</hi> of Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Let any body look over the <hi>Offers</hi> that <hi>King</hi> made, and eſpecially at the Iſle of <hi>Wight Treaty,</hi> and then tell me, Whether there was any Reaſon to bring the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Murther upon theſe Nations. I am not juſt if I don't ſay the <hi>Whigs</hi> are too ſoon diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and carry their Points too far, and that they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate their Numbers; The Men of the beſt Quality and Eſtates have generally a mind to Peace, and are not ſo eager for <hi>Critical Reformations.</hi> Some of the <hi>Whigs</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtart <hi>Grievances</hi> before others feel them, and are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding our very <hi>Fundamentals</hi> for the <hi>Chimera's</hi> of a <hi>warm Imagination,</hi> and a <hi>punctilious Nicety,</hi> which jollier Heads and ſweeter Natures can never comprehend; and at laſt they weaken themſelves by <hi>Subdiviſions:</hi> They ſpin their Thread too fine, their <hi>Speculations</hi> are ſcare Practical, and end in <hi>Viſion;</hi> Tho they are for <hi>Liberty</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> they are for <hi>Perſecution,</hi> for Fire and Fagot, for Extremity in <hi>Politicks.</hi> The Bulk of <hi>Freeholdors</hi> will ſtick by Eſſentials, but the <hi>Whigs</hi> almoſt Nick-name their own Notions, and then it is no wonder if the <hi>Tories</hi> take them for Scarecrows and Bulbeggers, and that the <hi>Propegaters</hi> of ſuch Doctrines are repreſented <hi>unreaſonable Men,</hi> rather <hi>Beautefeux</hi> than <hi>Patriots:</hi> Your out word your own Opinions, and you talk <hi>Hyperboles</hi> and <hi>Catachreſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Tories</hi> think you <hi>Lunaticks</hi> becauſe they don't underſtand your Language. you ought ſeriouſly to conſider your Numbers, and you will not find diſproportion enough between you and thoſe <hi>Tories</hi> to make it reaſonable that they ſhould wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe your <hi>State Creed;</hi> and perhaps there will be leſs reaſon if you look back and find that tho ſome <hi>fierce Men</hi> of that Party (and God knows there are ſuch in all Parties) may have been for <hi>ſcrewing up Monarchy</hi> too high, yet many that are for ſupporting the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>limitted ſucceſſive Monarchy,</hi> have always joyned in all honeſt and moderate Things. Indeed when King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second returned, his <hi>firſt Parliament</hi> gave him more Power than they were afterwards willing he ſhould keep; but were not the <hi>Whigs</hi> as mad at the <hi>Inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration</hi> of the Prince of <hi>Orange?</hi> If the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in the Reign of that Prince, did not hunt ſo hard when the <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> was on Foot; I ſuppoſe many of you are at this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> convinced you were <hi>too Keen,</hi> and that the Buſineſs was a little <hi>over Swore.</hi> If they oppoſed the <hi>Bill of Excluſion,</hi> without peradventure they were in the <hi>Right</hi> of it: For it was <hi>purely Perſonal</hi> in its Regards; loving one Man more than <hi>Liberty,</hi> and Hating another more than <hi>Slavery;</hi> and miſerable is that People whoſe Security is more from the <hi>Temper</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> than the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> I cannot but bemoan what we loſt by <hi>your heat</hi> at that Time. If you ſay the Church of <hi>England Quo Warranto'd Corporations,</hi> They did it no more than the <hi>Fanaticks Regulated</hi> them. I think it unjuſt to <hi>charge Parties</hi> with the Faults of particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. There was but a few of either Party concerned in either of thoſe <hi>evil Steps;</hi> and its as unjuſt to take away the Reputation of either Party for the Miſcarriages of thoſe few, as to take away <hi>Charters</hi> for <hi>perſonal Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adminiſtrations;</hi> and I am confident that even all the <hi>Non Swearers</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would have been willing to have aſſertained our <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and ſecured our <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> when the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came; they were weary of <hi>pretended unlimitted Prerogative,</hi> to ſay no more, and I think I ought not if I would pleaſe them, or you. But pray what harm had it been if we had not changed the Name of our King, if we had altered the complection of Affairs; is it not a ſhame, that Sir <hi>Thomas Clarges,</hi> and Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Muſgrave,</hi> &amp;c. ſhould have conſulted Amendment more than thoſe that have taken the Degree of Doctors at the <hi>King's head Club,</hi> and at <hi>Richard's</hi> Coffee-houſe? Is it not a ſhame that you would not make the Embryos of neceſſary Inſurrections, leſs li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to proſecution in the laſt Seſſion, and that you could in the Convention ſuſpend the <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> tho when you gave the Crown you declar'd it a fundamental right? If you have Liberty to elect Kings, why are you ſo An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at thoſe that will Chuſe their Old one again, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps upon more honeſt Limitations than you Created yours? The word Limitation puts me in mind, that I promiſed to ſhew that you are too violently apprehenſive of Slavery, and therefore I will once again ſay you did not make the beſt uſe of your Victories over King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, becauſe you brought them to a point wherein the Conſciences of moſt rebuked them, and wherein the generality were not likely to ſuccumb, and you were as indiſcreet in the management of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's timerous Nature, who would have denied ſcarce any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110066:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thing but the Bill of <hi>Excluſion</hi> at the time that that was firſt on Foot, and indeed would have found no Party to buoy him up in the denial of any thing elſe: To obviate your unreaſonable fears of Slavery, I beſeech you to conſider whether Hiſtory gives an Account of any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have been made Slaves but by their own Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to be ſo, unleſs by an entire Conqueſt; and I once again affirm, it is not in the Power of <hi>France</hi> to conquer <hi>England,</hi> unleſs by our own Diviſions; and thoſe Diviſions would ſoon ceaſe, if we did not oppoſe the bringing home King <hi>James</hi> upon civil Securities. The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> hates the Perſons of the <hi>Whigs,</hi> and more their Principles, and makes all thoſe of them he imploies, change them, or at leaſt act againſt them; yet their implacable hate to King <hi>James</hi> will not let them, tho they have ſo much puniſh'd him, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, forgive Errors in him, which they commend in this Man; and if King <hi>James</hi> is ever Reſtored it will be eaſy to miſrepreſent their Notions by reaſon of the Men that profeſs them: Whereas would they plead for their Liberties under a Reſtoration, and not talk in prejudice of the Eſtabliſh'd Worſhip of the Church (to pull down which is neither the Buſineſs, nor the deſire even of any wiſe Diſſenter) the Church of <hi>England</hi> will joyn to ask and expect all Things that can make our Conſtitution happy and Stable, not only under any Popiſh but under all Kings. Reflect ſeriouſly whether the body of the Nation, which is moſtly compoſed of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> has not been Strugling theſe laſt 50 Years for more Liberty; this may inſtruct the <hi>Whigs</hi> that they need not fear the loſs of it, and King <hi>James</hi> that he muſt give it. The nature of our Scituation, of our Tenures, of our Incloſures, and eſpecially of our People, is a full Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that we ſhall never looſe our beloved <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Whig</hi> Party are ſo unreaſonable, that they chuſe to embroil us in Civil Wars rather than to hearken to any Propoſals from King <hi>James,</hi> or joyn with others to ſend Propoſals to him. The Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Ceſſation of the <hi>Highlanders,</hi> have not ended the <hi>Jacobite</hi> Quarrel; and tho this Defeat of the <hi>French</hi> by Sea, damps the wild and viſſionary <hi>Jacobite,</hi> yet it will not put an end to our Miſeries: Were King <hi>James</hi> dead, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> would be thought on; and thoſe that believe ſucceſſive Monarchy, are very much (what ere you think) ſatisfied of his <hi>Legitimacy.</hi> But were he, and the Child of which the Queen is lately delivered of, and King <hi>James</hi> alſo dead, if the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> ſhould die, the Princeſs of <hi>Denmark</hi> muſt be a moſt reſigned Woman, if ſhe did not ask for her Right: Whatever others can, I can yet ſee nothing but Confuſion and Calamity, intollerable and eternal Taxes, together with the loſs of Trade, and Honour on the one hand, and on the other hand, our antient Plenty, and our ancient Government; without <hi>Sunderland,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remade Secretary of State, or a general Exciſe Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, which are the reſolv'd on Methods of King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam:</hi> But I muſt yet give an Account of the moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Hobgoblin of all, <hi>Popery.</hi> I believe as little of its Creed, and as ill of its Practices, as any body; but I would take a new Method to civilize thoſe wild Men that you think Beaſts of prey. I would treat them better; I would enfranchize them; I blame neither <hi>Papiſt</hi> nor <hi>Fanatick</hi> for being in a Plot, till they are impartially dealt with: And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t I can, and do, and ever did, and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall, comply with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not perſonal Concern makes me ſay this, but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Perſwaſion, that I have had theſe Twelve Years, That where a Nation is divided into Sects, <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> Matters ought to be diſtinct. As we manage the point, the Papiſts will be Vaſſals for the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and Spies for every Catholick Monarchy from whence they may hope a deliverance, as well as Flatterers of Prerogative; but if you would blend them with all the other Sects, they would not be taſted in the Compoſition, nor would they be looking for Succours from abroad. But when I have ſaid all this, let the Roman Catholicks at their peril endeavour to be invidiouſly Preferred, or engroſs the King, we can put a Bear-Skin upon them, when we pleaſe; And if a King of their perſwaſion will be the King of their party, the next Revolution will extirpate <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Royal Line</hi> to boot; and now we can cut off, and <hi>abdicate</hi> Kings in the face of the World: We ſhall learn Maſſacres, and turn into a perfect Common wealth. I will allow you Gentlemen to believe Tranſubſtantiation, but I adviſe you as a Friend not to truſt to Miracles; but to allow that natural weight will be too hard for all your Superfine projections: So that tho I am for your having utmoſt Liberty, and tho I am as much an Enemy to Civil Inquiſitions here, as to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, or rather irreligious one in <hi>Spain,</hi> yet I would have you remember that I ſay you are to have that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty only upon your good Behaviour. If King <hi>James</hi> comes in, if you will not as induſtriouſly as any other Party promote the general Good. If you will not be as Zealous for it as your Predeceſſors when they got <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> you will be a hated Faction ſtill, and find me too true a Prophet at laſt. I think the <hi>French</hi> never were, but I believe every body will allow that they have now no reaſon to be ſo Viſſionary as to expect to make us a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony; and if any <hi>Catholicks</hi> or mad <hi>Tories,</hi> ſtill expect Force from abroad, ſhall ſet King <hi>James</hi> upon the Throne, they are madder than any ſet of Men but thoſe <hi>Whigs</hi> that fear a <hi>French</hi> Conqueſt, and from thence <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have treated upon odd Things, and in an unuſual Manner, and perhaps ſhall have tired the Peruſer, but to ſpeak in a very few Words the drift of the whole. It is to invite all my Country-men to be ready to receive the King upon ſuch large and comprehenſive Meaſures, as ought to ſatisfy all Parties, it is to incline all Parties, to be reaſonable in their demands, and to perſuade King <hi>James</hi> to give ſuch Terms as the People will thank him for now, and will have, or eternally be reſtiffe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy; it is to perſwade all Engliſh men, to conſider <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Civil Matters</hi> a part; it is to incorporate all our Sects into one <hi>National Intereſt.</hi> It does allow <hi>Government</hi> from God, but the <hi>Specification</hi> from Men. It is not to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with <hi>Hereditary Monarchy,</hi> but deſires we may be ſafe in our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and that we ſhould Sacrifice them for the <hi>Publick</hi> againſt Enemies abroad, rather than by <hi>inteſtine Jars.</hi> In a word, all this Ramble is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to a new <hi>Magna Charta:</hi> To <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> which God grant may be the Concluſion of all our diſmal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances. I wiſh Men would rather caſt about in their thoughts how to draw ſuch a <hi>Magna Charta</hi> than to make oppoſition which can never determine the Controverſy, as long as any one Branch of the <hi>Right Line</hi> is alive. I wiſh they would rather think who ſhould Repreſent than who ſhould Fight for them.</p>
            <p>To conclude, I expect to pleaſe no one Party becauſe I appear to be of none bigotly, but write for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Good, tho I think what I have ſet down are Truths: Yet I fear they are too ſtrong to be digeſted, they do not cloſe with the Partialities of any ſort of Men; however they are well meant, and I leave the iſſue to the great Diſpoſer of all Things, and Men to jumble and cut, and be unfortunate, till they find by Experience according to the Title of this Diſcourſe, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honeſty,</hi> after all, <hi>is the beſt Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110066:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
